<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Hi! I&#39;m Adam. 😄</title>
        <link>http://adamr.io/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Hi! I&#39;m Adam. 😄</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="http://adamr.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title> Sacred Geometry: On Directing &#39;Disgraced&#39;</title>
            <link>http://adamr.io/posts/sacred-geometry/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://adamr.io/posts/sacred-geometry/</guid>
            <description>There is an unmatched clarity to creating art from limitation.
In my Wesleyan junior fall, I seized such an opportunity. I directed the very play that thrust me into the realm of theater.
Ayad Akhatar&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Disgraced&amp;rdquo; was first presented to me as an opportunity to leverage my identity as a young Desi male and perform several times as Hussein Malik / Abe Jensen, whose experience mirrors my own (to an extent, thankfully).</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is an unmatched clarity to creating art from limitation.</p>
<p>In my Wesleyan junior fall, I seized such an opportunity. I directed the very play that thrust me into
the realm of theater.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/sacred-geometry/stainedglass.jpg" alt="Stained glass."></p>
<p>Ayad Akhatar&rsquo;s &ldquo;Disgraced&rdquo; was first presented to me as an opportunity to leverage
my identity as a young Desi male and perform several times as Hussein Malik / Abe Jensen, whose experience mirrors my own (to an extent, thankfully). The Readers' Theater of Connecticut had reached out to Wesleyan&rsquo;s Muslim Chaplain and to its Theater Dept. querying for someone who fit the description (a rare moment where, for a man of color, &lsquo;fit the description&rsquo; was something undeniably positive).</p>
<p>At that time, I ached to act and probably would have accepted any role. I remember my freshman self dashing to the Office of Religious Life to meet with directors Anne Cassady and Richard Kamins, clearing my throat to try out for the part. No knowledge or preparation of the play beforehand, I was essentially cast because I was one of the first and only people to have responded to their casting call.</p>
<p>Fast forward to two years later; I was handing out sides for the parts I had grown to know almost as people in their own right. In my head, &lsquo;Isaac&rsquo;, &lsquo;Jory&rsquo;, &lsquo;Abe&rsquo;, &lsquo;Emily&rsquo;, and especially &lsquo;Amir&rsquo; were real, and spoke to me, and each of them was the type of person who would be indignant if I botched their casting.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;d like to say I didn&rsquo;t! I wouldn&rsquo;t know, for as I was steeped in weeks of rehearsal, the actors in front of me grew into their roles so well that, as far as I was concerned, they <em>were</em> the characters, just as I had become &lsquo;Abe&rsquo; when I embodied him years prior.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/sacred-geometry/directing.png" alt="Photograph by Thanmye Lagudu."></p>
<p>It was not a seamless beauty. We were, after all, university students (and in the case of one of my cast, a university employeee) for whom top grades and career aspirations were the priority. Second Stage, the production company sponsoring my play, is volunteer-based and entirely student-run, and our entire cast and crew had limited experience in theatrical production.</p>
<p>This was my first time directing, and although professional directing experience was available on Wesleyan&rsquo;s campus in the form of Directing I, II, and other courses, these were essentially inaccessible to me. I had always seen my theater major as a separate and smaller interest from my career path in software, I had never imagined that I would end up being one of the individuals on campus who would run a theater company, act in major productions, and direct a play.</p>
<p>Seven courses, frequent physical therapy, being the lights liaison of a major production company, and directing a play. And yet, I felt an odd sort of freedom, the kind where I was able to choose my own pain and look forward to seeing this production come together.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/sacred-geometry/d7.JPG" alt="Photograph by Elijah Comas."></p>
<p>Personal and logistic limitations lent the play a unique authenticity, a sense of things being handcrafted and incidental. The stage was not a grand proscenium but an improvised black box in the basement of Wesleyan&rsquo;s Malcolm X House. The lavish NYC apartment Akhtar describes was framed by pieces of furniture borrowed both from the Center for the Arts, the office of Wesleyan&rsquo;s theater technical director, and people&rsquo;s personal possessions. My lack of experience as the lights liaison meant I could barely figure out how to actually bring theatrical lights into the space, so off to Ikea we went to obtain remote controlled lighting peripherals, and off to my room I went to grab my floor lamp.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/sacred-geometry/d4.JPG" alt="Photograph by Elijah Comas."></p>
<p>But, I mean, Jesus. <em>Subhanallah</em>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m still in disbelief at how ragtag the process was and yet how cohesive the final product felt. Our limitations brought out a collective genius, where my team&rsquo;s experience in film and art translated to selecting the perfect wallpapers, furniture pieces, and props that could coexist in this communally crafted microcosm.</p>
<p>The aesthetic was a vibrant yet classy red, white, and dark shades of navy and black which cohered with the costume design and complemented by geometric patterns; the jazzy sound design provided this with a greater reality, ambience that cast judgment on the characters themselves. The set was flanked on the northeast by a handbuilt balcony setpiece that my set designer Angelica and her volunteer carpetners toiled to make which lent the illusion of an outer world, a clever method of masking the shattered glass prop that Arnaav needed to toss to the floor in a fit of rage.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/sacred-geometry/haha_isaac.JPG" alt="Photograph by Elijah Comas."></p>
<p>There not being any theatrical incandescent lighting meant the set needed to be lit entirely by &lsquo;naturals&rsquo; - a small table lamp near the &lsquo;fireplace&rsquo;, a floor lamp from my room, and LED strip lights near the &lsquo;lobby&rsquo; - all of which were tethered to wireless light dimmers that needed to be on cue with certain moments. This ended up being a rather cool element; even though audiences were familiar with how theatrical lighting systems were set up with lightboards and specialized software, our system was entirely improvised and home-made and set within the confines of this residential area. The space was truly transformed.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/sacred-geometry/d6.JPG" alt="Photograph by Elijah Comas."></p>
<p>I miss it, of course. I burn with nostalgia at this halcyonic winter, where I was provided both with freedom and restriction to collaborate and create a work of art that adhered so much to personal identity yet was blessed with community. It was a lighting flash, a moment trapped in amber and cast in flame. It could only have happened in my final year of college with this collective of individuals in particular.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know if I am even a good theatermaker, if I am a decent actor or director, but I know that I enjoyed seeing the final product, and I know that I ache with a desire to do more. Even in the midst of writing this, there is more that I want to say (specifically about <em>why</em> &lsquo;Disgraced&rsquo; deserves a Pulitzer, but that is for another time).</p>
<p>A final thank you to all of the individuals mentioned here, my cast and crew, my team. Some of the artists of the future are mentioned in this very program. To them, I give much 💕.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/sacred-geometry/disgraced_program.png" alt="Disgraced program."></p>
<p><em>Official publicity photographs courtesy of Elijah Comas &lsquo;22</em></p>
<p><em>That adorable directing photo courtesy of my Stage Manager Thanmye Lagudu &lsquo;20</em></p>
<p><img src="../../images/sacred-geometry/yay.jpg" alt="💕"></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>All the Difference | My UNICEF Winternship: Part III</title>
            <link>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-iii/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-iii/</guid>
            <description>My winter algorithms course at Wesleyan had me falling in love with the graph data structure. Vertices and edges entwined to form a vast web that could abstract anything from a series of highways to a social network, and with so much literature and research on how to conduct analysis on graphs, I sought the holy grail of capturing an entire country’s road network in this structure so I could leverage shortest-path algorithms.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My winter algorithms course at Wesleyan had me falling in love with the graph data structure. Vertices and edges entwined to form a vast web that could abstract anything from a series of highways to a social network, and with so much literature and research on how to conduct analysis on graphs, I sought the holy grail of capturing an entire country’s road network in this structure so I could leverage shortest-path algorithms.</p>
<p>So imagine my surprise when I found the perfect library - Geoff Boeing’s OSMNX, which uses OpenStreetMap APIs and Python’s NetworkX graphing library to convert roads, pathways, streets, etc. into a graph that one could manipulate and conduct analysis. Just take a look at Manhattan&rsquo;s roads visualized as a graph data structure - through code, I could walk around the city, see how long each road was, and most importantly - compute shortest-paths between sites!</p>
<p><img src="../../images/my-unicef-winternship/osmnx_nyc.png" alt="Manhattan in OSMNX"></p>
<p>To recall the problem statement for Magicbox - for each location (e.g. school, population point) in a given list of geographic coordinates, identify the distance / travel time to the nearest health facility (or other kind of location). I referred to the schools or population points as origin sites, and the health facilities as destination sites.</p>
<p>Therefore, given a graph of the road network and the two source and destination datasets (usually .geojson files containing latitudes and longitudes for schools and health facilities) - The algorithm would run as follows:</p>
<ol>
<li>For each origin site, find its nearest node on the graph, we label this as the origin node and save the distance between the site and the node</li>
<li>Do the same for each destination site but label the nearest node as the destination node</li>
<li>Compute all pairs of shortest paths between origin node and each destination node, to optimize, we use an approach known as dynamic programming to save shortest paths so that when two sites share the same source node, we don’t recompute, but lookup from a table instead</li>
<li>Once a shortest path is successfully found, add the length of that path to the distance between the origin site and the origin node, and to the distance between the destination site and the destination node - voila !</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="../../images/my-unicef-winternship/rad_roads.png" alt="Routing in Manhattan">
<em>A routing example in OSMNX.</em></p>
<p>To optimize further, I told the algorithm to first compute straight-line distance for all origin sites, and only compute the routed distance if the straight-line distance was greater than one kilometer, since that distance could be reliably walked.</p>
<p>I consulted with my supervisors and members of the data science team about whether or not I had the right approach, and I would continue to refine as I incorporated the feedback I received. The example below shows a Jupyter Notebook excerpt from my code:</p>
<p><img src="../../images/my-unicef-winternship/jupyter_routing.png" alt="Jupyter Notebook routing example."></p>
<p>My algorithm was complete, and eager to show this to my supervisors, I loaded it on a souped-up virtual machine that the Magicbox developers would be using to preprocess all the data. I wrote two utilities - one that retrieved all the road graphs from OSMNX and stored it on the VM, another to compute the distances. Although computations for straight-line distance were reliably speedy, to my disappointment, routed distance computations took their sweet time even with the dynamic programming optimization.</p>
<p>This challenge - optimizing the distance calculations to ingest huge datasets - was what would ultimately test my resourcefulness and problem-solving, and I developed two means of addressing this - refactoring my code to include concurrency, and porting these graphs to a faster graph library.</p>
<p>Concurrency is the ability of a program’s different components to run out-of-order - for example, to leverage the benefits of a multi-core CPU, different functions could be assigned to different cores so that they could all run in parallel and return an output faster than if they were done in order. This meant I had to identify the pieces of my code that could be run out-of-order - for example, when computing shortest paths between all pairs of nodes in the graph, one path isn’t dependent on another graph, so I could actually compute them all at once!</p>
<p>I knew just what to refactor, but I knew that Python’s NetworkX library could still not handle the load of all of these computations at a desirable pace. With luck, Geoff Boeing has provided a method in OSMNX to convert NetworkX graphs to iGraph format, a different Python graph library which uses C++ bindings for greater speedup.</p>
<p>However, iGraph presented multiple difficulties when attempting to install on my machine and the virtual machine, so I decided to experiment with Docker. Docker allows one to run virtualized containers that are bundled with their own software and libraries for easier development, so I decided to run a container that was already configured with both OSMNX and iGraph.</p>
<p>It worked beautifully.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/my-unicef-winternship/global_output_kepler.png" alt="Global output, color representing distance to nearest healthsite.">
<em>Global output, color representing distance to nearest healthsite.</em></p>
<p><img src="../../images/my-unicef-winternship/dist_by_color_height_by_pop.png" alt="Additional output in kepler.gl with color representing distance, and height representing population.">
<em>Additional output in kepler.gl with color representing distance, and height representing population.</em></p>
<p>It was mesmerizing to see my terminal spit out successful outputs at a blazing pace, and when I opened up the final result on kepler.gl, I was so elated at how it all seem to cohere with my previous results.</p>
<p>I continued to polish up my code as the start of my final semester approached, improving documentation and refactoring method and variable names for clarity. The UNICEF innovation team threw me a small impromptu party as I prepared to pack my bags and head to Grand Central to depart to Middletown, Connecticut.</p>
<p>My previous questions of “how did I get here?” and “what do I do?” became “man, already?”. My hunger to finish school and take a deep dive into the world of software development and data science was intensified, and even as I was inundated with new assignments and theatrical responsibilities, I found myself adding more optimizations to my repositories and editing documentation.</p>
<p>In mid-February, I gave my final presentation to the UNICEF Innovation team - “The Road(s) Not Taken: Mapping Vulnerability through Data Preprocessing and Network Algorithms” - describing my approach and results. I slipped in a not-so-subtle Robert Frost reference, alluding to the work I had done on roads, but also as a personal reminder.</p>
<p>This internship was a test of my ambition and ability. It allowed me to take leaps of faith and trusted my capacity to internalize technical concepts to manifest them into real-world solutions. It warms me to this day to see the code that I had crafted in two months being used for a true purpose, and it has been the ultimate encouragement in getting myself out there and tackling further challenges. In deciding to work for UNICEF as a Magicbox Engineering Intern that winter, I took the road less travelled by - and that has made all the difference.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/my-unicef-winternship/unicef_innovation.jpeg" alt="The UNICEF Innovation team.">
<em>Thank you everyone! With love, Adam.</em></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Go the Distance | My UNICEF Winternship: Part II</title>
            <link>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-ii/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-ii/</guid>
            <description>“Ah, no wonder all of these distances are millions of miles away - the input file had the latitudes and longitudes flipped!”
I pressed my fingers against my temple and giggled in relief, wishing I had caught this error before my recent code push. We were nearing the halfway point of my winternship, and I had begun prototyping a utility that would assist Magicbox developers in mapping healthcare accessibility.
I hadn’t expected my curious pursuit of an unresolved issue on the Magicbox Github repository to be this engaging and fun - but I knew I was on the right track.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>“Ah, no wonder all of these distances are millions of miles away - the input file had the latitudes and longitudes flipped!”</p>
<p>I pressed my fingers against my temple and giggled in relief, wishing I had caught this error before my recent code push. We were nearing the halfway point of my winternship, and I had begun prototyping a utility that would assist Magicbox developers in mapping healthcare accessibility.</p>
<p>I hadn’t expected my curious pursuit of an unresolved issue on the Magicbox Github repository to be this engaging and fun - but I knew I was on the right track. Each minor frustration was further evidence that the training wheels of my university’s computer science curriculum were coming off.</p>
<p>![A problem to be tackled.]../../images/my-unicef-winternship/git_issue.png)</p>
<p>The problem statement was straightforward - for each location in a given list of geographic coordinates, identify the distance / travel time to the nearest health facility. For example, we might have a list of schools for a given country, with each school having attributes such as size, curriculum type, internet connectivity, etc.</p>
<p>We sought to add “distance to nearest health site” as an attribute for these schools, and to use Magicbox visualization tools such as kepler.gl to present these geographic points and have the option to color-code them by distance to the nearest healthsite - akin to the following picture, which ended being our final output:</p>
<p>![A kepler.gl visualization of schools color-coded by distance to health facility.]../../images/my-unicef-winternship/kepler_color_coded.png)
<em>A kepler.gl visualization of schools color-coded by distance to health facility.</em></p>
<p>Physical access to health facilities is something taken for granted in dense urban metropoles like New York City, but in the rural and remote settlements that populate third-world UNICEF programme countries, distance and travel time to health sites is critical to whether or not an area’s infrastructure is prepared to rapidly provide medical services, and has an impact on controlling disease outbreak or childhood mortality. In rural Nigeria, utilization of health care facilities has been found to decrease exponentially with distance. It was apparent that computing and visualizing access to these facilities across all UNICEF programme countries would be of great value.</p>
<p>Of course, although schools, population points, and health facilities were the specific types of locations the Magicbox developers were using, the problem statement is agnostic as to what each geographic coordinate contained. I approached the issue by treating it as a generalized nearest neighbor problem, and identified two notions of ‘distance’ - straight-line, and routed.</p>
<p>Straight-line distance is the absolute geographic distance between two points, which requires a specific distance metric known as Haversine due to the Earth’s curvature. It does not factor in natural barriers or manmade infrastructure, for example, if I knew the straight-line distance from my home in Queens to my friend’s house in Brooklyn, walking an uninterrupted path to there would be impossible.</p>
<p>Instead, I must take into account routed distance, which uses transportation networks to route the path from one site to another. This means that depending on the nature of this network, it may more physical distance to get from Queens to Brooklyn since the train I took must stay on its track and pass through Manhattan. One can infer that the developing infrastructures in the countries we were analyzing may lead to greater disparities in the straight-line vs. routed distance - i.e., how far away a facility was, and how long it actually takes to get there, which has a huge impact.</p>
<p>![Example output with Colombia population points.]../../images/my-unicef-winternship/routing_2.png)
<em>A SQL Query running on population points.</em></p>
<p>Of course, all of these distance computations required speedy and efficient algorithms that could scale to hundreds of thousands of points. For computing straight-line distances for a set of points, I opted to use the popular Python machine learning library scikit-learn and its ball tree data structure to conduct a nearest neighbor search.</p>
<p>Trees are a popular data structure that allows partitioning datasets to speed up queries, such as nearest neighbor search, and scikit-learn’s ball tree allowed me to enter geographic latitude and longitude coordinates and came bundled with a haversine distance metric - sweet !</p>
<p>After familiarizing myself with tools such as numpy and pandas, I was able to load in a dataset of points and, for each point, find the nearest neighbor from the other set of points - i.e. for each school, I could quickly compute the distance in meters to the nearest health site. Occasionally - as mentioned at the beginning of this article - I would come across data entry errors where the X and Y coordinates were flipped, or an input was in kilometers, or no distance was returned.</p>
<p>Trial and error was key - I was sufficiently confident in my algorithms and data structures to know that my procedure was right, and I was in the right headspace to keep working, keep tweaking, keep twisting (there were quite a few moments where I used Google Maps to verify a correct distance - I always pumped my fist in excitement when it worked).</p>
<p>![Example output with Colombia population points.]../../images/my-unicef-winternship/routing_1.png)
<em>Example output with Colombia population points.</em></p>
<p>My supervisors Mike and Marcella would hold me accountable through a daily 5 pm scrum that was either through Skype call or at the office. Scrum is a practice from agile methodology, where we convened to describe what we’ve done, as well as roadblocks and aspirations. I also attended less frequent full team meetings where we made adjustments to a UNICEF Innovation Trello board to monitor our progress. Magicbox also has a public Gitter channel where the open-source community can participate, and I would also check it and make inquiries about my approach to other developers.</p>
<p>Working with geospatial data felt empowering and gratifying; with a few keystrokes, I was manipulating points on the globe and performing extensive computations to address an important issue. But straight-line distances were only the first step - check out part III to see how I leveraged my CS skills and an excellent Python library to tackle routed distance and sign off from my internship !</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Roads Yet Taken | My UNICEF Winternship: Part I</title>
            <link>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-i/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-i/</guid>
            <description>In my mother’s childhood, when Bangladesh herself was newly-born, her father would bring home blankets emblazoned with the UNICEF logo, a comforting blue. This same blue, painted on the canvas banners of the UNICEF lobby, where I waited for my supervisor Mike Fabrikant to sign me in for my first day as a Software Engineering intern.
As I leaned against the couch in the lobby, I traced a route in my mind’s eye — from the Dhaka hospital where I was born, to the teensy-weensy lead-chipped apartment my parents and I sidled into when we arrived here in the new millennium, to the finale of my academic career at Wesleyan where I finished up my B.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my mother’s childhood, when Bangladesh herself was newly-born, her father would bring home blankets emblazoned with the UNICEF logo, a comforting blue. This same blue, painted on the canvas banners of the UNICEF lobby, where I waited for my supervisor Mike Fabrikant to sign me in for my first day as a Software Engineering intern.</p>
<p>As I leaned against the couch in the lobby, I traced a route in my mind’s eye — from the Dhaka hospital where I was born, to the teensy-weensy lead-chipped apartment my parents and I sidled into when we arrived here in the new millennium, to the finale of my academic career at Wesleyan where I finished up my B.A. in Computer Science and Theater.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/my-unicef-winternship/unicef_building.jpeg" alt="UNICEF building"></p>
<p>“How did I get here?”</p>
<p>This question was fueled by a Matcha-Yerba Mate infusion I had concocted that morning, heated with a silent prayer that the pen-and-paper knowledge gained from my Computer Science courses would translate well to this particular opportunity. My internship was already on its way; just a week after final exams ended that semester, I was installing React packages and running Docker containers to view UNICEF’s Magicbox platform for myself.</p>
<p>Magicbox is an open-source multifaceted collaborative platform for aggregating, ingesting, and understanding the big data corresponding to specific phenomena in UNICEF programme countries, from connectivity to disease outbreaks. Crafting visualizations and developing machine learning models from the data collected can go a long way in predicting and planning for natural disasters, epidemics, or other exogenous factors that may disrupt wellbeing.</p>
<p>I knew quite well about the phenomena faced by developing countries on the other side of the world — whether it be my performative writing seminar where race and class was on everyone’s breath, or my course on social entrepreneurship and philanthropy — Bangladesh and/or its third-world problems were a persistent thread. Having moved to the U.S. so young, I was only familiar with the sensations of my country of origin — the heat and humidity, the fabrics and clear skies — distinct from the powerful and monolithic view of the United Nations towers from the UNICEF innovation office.</p>
<p>There, Mike and my other supervisor, Marcella Maki, helped me discern my route through this internship, which was partly remote and partly onsite. My fellow intern, Courage Angeh, was working remotely from Cameroon, which made for an interesting dynamic as I was often one of two interns present in the UNICEF Innovation offices.</p>
<p>I couldn’t believe how fortunate I was, that I’d be able to look after my family and prepare for my final semester at Wesleyan while transmuting the conceptual into the concrete. These next two months were spent in a deep dive of scientific computing, geospatial analysis, virtual machines, and plenty of tea — of course. In Part II of this piece, I will describe how I tackled healthsite accessibility, the challenges faced, and why it affirmed my desire to code with purpose.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/my-unicef-winternship/mike_and_adam.jpeg" alt="Me and Mike"></p>
<p><em>Me and my supervisor, Mike Fabrikant.</em></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title> The African-American Mecca You&#39;ve Never Heard of </title>
            <link>http://adamr.io/posts/african-american-mecca/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://adamr.io/posts/african-american-mecca/</guid>
            <description>A 20th Century paradise, built from the ground up, sustained entirely by an overwhelmingly Black American population.
This &amp;lsquo;Black Wall Street&amp;rsquo; was packed with business centers, hotels, cafes, shopping malls, high-performing schools and homes featuring modern conveniences.
You probably never heard of this place, the suburban community of Greenwood in Tulsa, Oklahoma. It may not have been in any history textbook you&amp;rsquo;ve read, or Netflix documentary you watched at 3 in the morning.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A 20th Century paradise, built from the ground up, sustained entirely by an overwhelmingly Black American population.</p>
<p>This &lsquo;Black Wall Street&rsquo; was packed with business centers, hotels, cafes, shopping malls, high-performing schools and homes featuring modern conveniences.</p>
<p>You probably never heard of this place, the suburban community of Greenwood in Tulsa, Oklahoma. It may not have been in any history textbook you&rsquo;ve read, or Netflix documentary you watched at 3 in the morning. It might not have even been brought up during Black History Month, despite all the lip service paid to figures like MLK Jr. and Malcolm X.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/african-american-mecca/greenwood_1.jpg" alt="A scene in Greenwood"></p>
<p>A thriving, technologically superior African-American neighborhood, existing decades prior to the Civil Rights Movement? Sounds empowering and inspirational, especially considering the rhetoric spat out by politicians and media figures concerning the black community, even today.</p>
<p>As a South Asian immigrant, my presence in academic institutions and workplaces communicates the &lsquo;model minority&rsquo; narrative to society, that my family and individuals like me are &lsquo;inherently&rsquo; capable of uplifting ourselves out of rigid socioeconomic conditions through intellect and grit.</p>
<p>This same narrative is not granted to black Americans, however, who are vilified in the media as being disadvantaged due to their own accord. The renowned &ldquo;Black Wall Street&rdquo; says otherwise, but unfortunately, it seems there is great care in wiping it off the record. Just as it had been wiped off the map.</p>
<p>Indeed, on May 31st and June 1st of 1921, members of the white community in Tulsa carried out a vicious attack on ground and from the air on the African-American community. Over 30 blocks of the neighborhood were demolished by airstrikes and bombs, 300 black people were killed, 800 admitted to hospitals, and over 6,000 were detained.</p>
<p>For the black veterans of WWI, they would have been reliving the horrors of combat in their own neighborhood. Dynamite, turpentine bombs, machine guns, gas&hellip;. all were being deployed by American citizen unto American citizen. Later investigations showed the city of Tulsa to have conspired with the white mob, hence why no fire alarms sounded and why police joined in, firing machine guns into the black crowd. A travesty.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/african-american-mecca/bws_memorial.jpg" alt="Black Wall Street Memorial"></p>
<p>The former success of Greenwood and the massacre&rsquo;s events were given no mention in town, city or state histories. Although it had been initiated after armed black citizens were attempting to prevent a lynching at the police station, historical records at the time shifted the blame towards the black population for &lsquo;instigating the riot&rsquo;.</p>
<p>Such was the story of Greenwood and its accompanying massacre, unheard of for almost eight decades until 1996 when the state legislature established the Tulsa Race Riot Commission to gather survivors' anecdotes, collect more information and correct the historical record. They even recommended reparations to the survivors' descendants.</p>
<p>Still, this event is not taught enough and its history must be proliferated. Students and society in general need to understand this one instance of black American brilliance, and how swiftly it was taken away as white citizens and the State conspired acts of domestic terrorism.</p>
<p>African-Americans and their allies must keep the memory of Black Wall Street in their hearts, for the goal of the Black Lives Matter movement and Civil Rights in general is to remove the notion that &lsquo;Black&rsquo; and &lsquo;Wall Street&rsquo; do not belong in the same sentence.</p>
<p>That the principles of hard work and self-sufficiency definitely do apply to black communities. That the state has taken an active hand in preventing the upward mobility of these communities by reinforcing systems of segregation through economic policy and mass incarceration.</p>
<p>So when politicians, when media figures like Donald Trump stand up at the podium and talk down to Black Americans while burning the image of devastated and violent black communities into the collective unconscious, we know better. We must engage in collective remembrance and retell the story of the minority experience in America. Do not forget.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title> Red, Black, Cyberpunk | 5 Awesome Retro Gadgets </title>
            <link>http://adamr.io/posts/red-black-cyberpunk/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://adamr.io/posts/red-black-cyberpunk/</guid>
            <description>We see our modern consumer electronics, from our Macbooks, iPhones,and Samsung Galaxies to even smart refrigerators, as exemplifying the endpoint of design progression. Sleek, dark, minimalist form has become the aim of hardware engineers, and the masses fall head over heels for it - I know I do.
But let&amp;rsquo;s step into the 80&amp;rsquo;s and 90&amp;rsquo;s for a mo&#39; and peer into an era where consumer electronics were just getting a foothold, and manufacturers had to experiment with a plethora of design choices.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We see our modern consumer electronics, from our Macbooks, iPhones,and Samsung Galaxies to even smart refrigerators, as exemplifying the endpoint of design progression. Sleek, dark, minimalist form has become the aim of hardware engineers, and the masses fall head over heels for it - I know I do.</p>
<p>But let&rsquo;s step into the 80&rsquo;s and 90&rsquo;s for a mo' and peer into an era where consumer electronics were just getting a foothold, and manufacturers had to experiment with a plethora of design choices. Sometimes this meant ugly electronics with poor color schemes that didn&rsquo;t age particularly well, serving as antique pieces collecting dust in dear Grandma&rsquo;s attic. But sometimes there were devices which struck a balance between minimalism and a sexy, hi-tech almost futuristic appearance that, although would stick out like a sore thumb in your pocket or living room (or give you a sore thumb), are still a treat for the eyes.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>1. Sony DC-88 Discman</strong></p>
<p>Sony dominated the former dedicated portable music player market, particularly with the Walkman brand which allowed folks to pop in their favorite cassette, plug in their favorite headphones (with the help of that classic and will-never-be-forgotten 3.5 mm jack) and jam on the streets.</p>
<p>Once music CD&quot;s grew more ubiquitous, Sony did all they could to hop onto that bandwagon and offer consumers an ultraportable means of playing them. So in 1988 they released the DC-88 Discman, a music player smaller than the actual CD&rsquo;s containing said music.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/red-black-cyberpunk/walkman.jpg" alt="Sony DC-88 Discman">
<em>Source: The Walkman Archive</em></p>
<p>Although it was intended for smaller discs, the DC-88 was still designed with regular CD&rsquo;s in mind, with the CD itself spinning partway outside of the device.</p>
<p>In the end, the DC-88 is a pretty little thing with a huge impracticality issue. You wouldn&rsquo;t want to stick this in your pocket - ever, unless you were looking for a painful and quick method of ruining both your music CD&rsquo;s and the inside of your pants.</p>
<p>At the very least, I&rsquo;d slice pizza with it.</p>
<p><strong>2. Sony Hit-Bit 101</strong></p>
<p>The 80&rsquo;s was when more and more homes began to purchase and own computers as living room mainstays, wonderful little novelties that probably won&rsquo;t help you get your homework done today but were fascinating machines nonetheless.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/red-black-cyberpunk/hitbit.jpg" alt="Sony Hit-Bit 101">
<em>Source: MSX Resource Center</em></p>
<p>The Sony Hit-Bit 101 is one such computer loaded with the MSX1 operating system. Released in 1984, it came with built-in software such as a memo and address book, and oddly enough, boasted a joystick where the arrow keys on a keyboard would have been.</p>
<p>Though such a decision would make sense in a time when home computers seemed more like novelty toys for playing video games than serious productivity machines. It certainly looks toy-ish, albeit a very gorgeous one, with an arresting red which catches the eye and flairs with style, and mechanical keys that no doubt offer a greater level of response and satisfaction than a lot of laptop keyboards do today.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the regular grey model isn&rsquo;t nearly a visually stimulating as its scarlet counterpart, with only Japanese consumers being able to buy the latter. Bah, humbug.</p>
<p><strong>3. Sega Master System</strong>
<img src="../../images/red-black-cyberpunk/mastersystem.png" alt="Sega Master System">
<em>Source: Nostalgia Nerd</em></p>
<p>The 80&rsquo;s saw an all-out video game console war between Sega and Nintendo, the tycoons of comfy-couch gaming, and in retrospect, both companies offered fun machines for playing an assortment of rich and colorful games. In comparison to Sega&rsquo;s Genesis system and Nintendo&rsquo;s NES and SNES, the Sega Master System wasn&rsquo;t nearly as popular in the American market and lacked the expansive libraries enjoyed by its succesor and competitors.</p>
<p>Still, kick me if that machine doesn&rsquo;t look stunning. Slim and simple with a red and black color scheme, out of all the 80&rsquo;s consoles, this is one I&rsquo;d still want to display on a coffee table. Unlike Nintendo&rsquo;s grey-colored consoles, which end up turning piss yellow over the years without proper care, Sega wisely decided to mold their consoles out of dark plastic, creating a more timeless look that complements the television sets it was placed under.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I tend not to enjoy many games on the Master System library, even though I love the way the controller feels as well. Maybe I ought to give this retro machine another try, but as for now, the SMS being eye candy is sufficient.</p>
<p><strong>4. Sony TC-D5M Analog Audiocassette Player</strong>
<img src="../../images/red-black-cyberpunk/cassette.jpg" alt="Sony TC-D5M Analog Audiocassette Player">
<em>Source: Walkman Central</em></p>
<p>Think about this - this was considered a portable device, that people who strap to their necks and lug around. Take a moment to give thanks for how feather-light your smartphones are&hellip; done? Ok.</p>
<p>To be fair, it does put the punk in cyberpunk. A mishmash of dials, visible machinery parts, analog dial indicators, and even a very visible mono speaker on the top of the device - this baby doesn&rsquo;t try to hide what it is, it&rsquo;s proud of its crowded appearance. And that does give the TC-D5M a certain stylish charm, even if I would never fathom using the device, it&rsquo;s certainly a nice look as to what constituted quality aesthetic design in 1978. Yes, I&rsquo;m cheating a bit, but it&rsquo;s only two years away from the 80&rsquo;s!</p>
<p>Oh, and this hunk took &lsquo;D&rsquo; batteries. Anyone got a spare?</p>
<p><strong>5. Sharp X1</strong>
<img src="../../images/red-black-cyberpunk/sharpx1.png" alt="Sharp X1">
<em>Source: OLD-COMPUTERS.com Museum</em></p>
<p>My oh my.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m ending this little trip through time with a piece of machinery I still scour eBay for in the vain hope that I could display this technological delight in my home and toy around with. The X1 series was released between 1982 and 1988 by Sharp - but only in Japan. So while the West had to stomach dull looking grey or beige monitors and keyboards, Japanese consumers could indulge in the red glory that is this part-home computer part-game console. That&rsquo;s right - through the insertion of floppy discs in later iterations of the series - one could play video games designed for the PC-Engine game console, even being able to plug in a gamepad.</p>
<p>The presentation of the X1 catches the eye with how vertically aligned all the elements seem to be as well as how the red is properly balanced out with the additional grey and black components. The monitor can actually be used as a TV independent of the computer machine, which makes it ideal for retro gaming. The X1&rsquo;s appearance as a whole definitely encapsulates the pop culture image of a &lsquo;computer&rsquo;, and a part of my heart wishes for manufacturers today to make computers that looked like the Sharp X1 but are just as powerful as our current Windows and Apple machines.</p>
<p>Hey, a guy can dream.</p>
<hr>
<p>If you&rsquo;re a tech or retro enthusiast, these blasts from the past might have quenched that thirst for old-but-gold electronics. If you&rsquo;re not, and you&rsquo;re just going &ldquo;huh?&rdquo; as you cling to the ebony keys of your Macbook Pro and send another Snap on your paper-thin iPhone 6, remember, the process of designing those robust and beautiful electronics had to start from somewhere.</p>
<p>Now if you&rsquo;ll excuse me, there&rsquo;s an eBay auction I have to keep an eye on&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
