<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>algorithms on Hi! I&#39;m Adam. 😄</title>
    <link>http://adamr.io/tags/algorithms/</link>
    <description>Recent content in algorithms on Hi! I&#39;m Adam. 😄</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://adamr.io/tags/algorithms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>All the Difference | My UNICEF Winternship: Part III</title>
      <link>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-iii/</guid>
      <description>My winter algorithms course at Wesleyan had me falling in love with the graph data structure. Vertices and edges entwined to form a vast web that could abstract anything from a series of highways to a social network, and with so much literature and research on how to conduct analysis on graphs, I sought the holy grail of capturing an entire country’s road network in this structure so I could leverage shortest-path algorithms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Go the Distance | My UNICEF Winternship: Part II</title>
      <link>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-ii/</guid>
      <description>“Ah, no wonder all of these distances are millions of miles away - the input file had the latitudes and longitudes flipped!”
I pressed my fingers against my temple and giggled in relief, wishing I had caught this error before my recent code push. We were nearing the halfway point of my winternship, and I had begun prototyping a utility that would assist Magicbox developers in mapping healthcare accessibility.
I hadn’t expected my curious pursuit of an unresolved issue on the Magicbox Github repository to be this engaging and fun - but I knew I was on the right track.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Roads Yet Taken | My UNICEF Winternship: Part I</title>
      <link>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://adamr.io/posts/unicef-winternship-pt-i/</guid>
      <description>In my mother’s childhood, when Bangladesh herself was newly-born, her father would bring home blankets emblazoned with the UNICEF logo, a comforting blue. This same blue, painted on the canvas banners of the UNICEF lobby, where I waited for my supervisor Mike Fabrikant to sign me in for my first day as a Software Engineering intern.
As I leaned against the couch in the lobby, I traced a route in my mind’s eye — from the Dhaka hospital where I was born, to the teensy-weensy lead-chipped apartment my parents and I sidled into when we arrived here in the new millennium, to the finale of my academic career at Wesleyan where I finished up my B.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
